so there's a few more suta exits that we
have here and these will they cover
various topics which we also addressed
in some of our previous talks but he
won't had to go through it again maybe
say some other things about it how
people think about it from different
angle so the first excerpt is from on
Goethe and Gaia 668 mmm and goes because
that a big who takes pleasure in company
who delights in company who is engaged
in the pleasure of company who takes
pleasure in groups who delights in
groups who is engaged in the pleasure of
groups that he will find pleasure in
seclusion when alone that is not
possible not finding pleasure in
seclusion when alone that he will pick
up the sign of the mind
chipton Lolita this is not possible not
picking up the sign of the mind that he
would fulfill the right view that's not
possible not having fulfilled the right view that
not having fulfilled the right view that
he would fulfill right composure
Samadhi that's not possible
not having fulfilled right composure
that he will abandon the fattest that is
not possible and not having abandoned
the fattest that he will realize Nibbana
that is not possible so
the whole point here as it can be seen
is that one needs to have grasped picked
up sign of the mind now that might sound
sort of mystical to somebody but sign of
the mind Chetan Amita literally means
the characteristics signs tokens of that
which mind is so not having the sign of
the mind that's that's the state of an
average person's mind so you need to
delight you need to first make effort to
avoid company dwell in solitude and then
find pleasure in that seclusion so
literally stop deferring seclusion over
company regardless of the company even
if it's the best possible company you
would still prefer seclusion so that is
a necessary basis to pick to start
picking and discerning these
characteristics tokens properties of
that which mind is so that and the
important difference here it's not like
that you'd sit down and psychologize and
sort of contrived these various
properties that you think belong to the
mind but generally discern them for what
they are on the level of the mind so
you're not putting them there you're
seeing them for what else you you're
looking for the properties of the mind
which means you're developing basically
a certain recognition of that which mine
is because mind is defined by its
properties the sign of the mind so you
want to how to discern the
characteristics of the mind you need to
have been dwelling in solitude and not
in company for a sufficient amount of
time probably work through boredom
anxiety restlessness and all the other
hindrances once you've worked through it
you start developing you start
preferring that that solitude you start
developing the pleasure in it in in that
seclusion and on account of that around
let's say around that time you could
then start well by that time you would
be more familiar that's where like that
with that which mind is because you
wouldn't be distracting yourself from it
you wouldn't be engaging with sensuality
or in company so you leave yourself no
other choice but to be living with your
own mind and if you start living with
your own mind which is all most people
avoid on the day-to-day basis if you
start living with your own mind you will
then start discerning its inherent
characteristics and that is the
necessary basis to become a sort of
owner to develop the right view there is
no right view without that sign of the
mind without knowing what the mind is
without seeing it as a phenomenon it's
impossible to develop the right view
unless you know exactly what your mind
is as in understand it
see that sign of the mind oh this is the
what what mind as a phenomenon as a
thing is and if a person is positive
like what is there to understand well
see most people's views about the mind I
are the views that they're derived from
the senses that then you apply to your
mind that's often people approach mind
like scientifically medically even
psychologically but none of those things
that the mind might proceed those things
so you cannot accurately describe
discern see them present as they are
characteristics of the mind by using the
sense sense data and inputs in input of
your senses because the mind does not
appear in any of the senses so what is
then the mind it's not a mystical if
something mystical about it is because
the whole direction is is to a peg
because of the the people inevitably
sort of spending the live distracting
so from their own mind so the slightest
thought in the direction of what the
mind might be on its own terms it's just
it's just overwhelmingly ambiguous so
that's why it's so hard to see the mind
and understanding mind as the Buddha
said in the other suitors but in order
to do so you need to do so if you want
to get the right view
so not picking up the side of the mind
the big who would fulfill right view
that's simply not possible it's
inconceivable and that should also shed
some light on on on people who kind of
have their tongue help but hope for some
special experiences to come out of the
meditation or practice and so on
including like the the attainments of
the Sato party and higher more often
than not it's assumed to be this this
overwhelmingly kind of entering this
this experience and you can't put it
into words and so on but whatever that
experience might be you want to ask
yourself well have I understood mine is
a phenomenon on account of which I had
this experience and if you can't put it
in the words means you haven't
understood it as simple as that
so whatever experience it was doesn't
matter how pleasant how uplifting how
out-of-this-world it was it's irrelevant
it's not the experience you should be
seeking out if it happens happens not
your problem what you want to seek out
is understanding the sign of the mind
thus you can develop and understand the
right view and that's not given that
does not occur spontaneously that occurs
through your own effort of that
development so fulfilling than the right
view or rather not having fulfilled
review that he would have Samadhi that's
not possible so that's another thing
very common misconception is that you
can do Samadhi correctly you can
practice Buddhist meditation correctly
knowing that you don't even have the
right view and then usual argument for
for that is well I
my meditation helps me nobody says it's
not helpful but it doesn't mean it's
right there's a minute on the level of
of freeing you from suffering that the
Buddha the Buddha said is the beginning
of the Dhamma so the party that's the
level you should be aiming for so the
you can practice Samadhi without sorta
body it's not possible then you can
practice correctly so if you don't have
the right view it doesn't matter how
helpful your Samadhi is it's not the
right Samadhi
because right Samadhi is not determined
but what you deem helpfulness is it's
determined by the right view which is
determined by grasping the sign of the
mind discerning the mind is a thing as a
phenomena on its own terms which is
redetermination in seclusion not just
forcing yourself in seclusion which is
determined by not being engaged with
groups not delighting in groups not
delighting in people not the lighting in
camaraderie in company in in in hanging
out and and so on so having a having
develop the right view you can then
develop the right Samadhi because that's
basically what right SMUD is composing
that right view to the extent necessary
for final knowledge for outer hundred
that's which says furthermore not having
fulfilled that right Samadhi that that
monk would abandon the fetters I become
an arahant
that's not possible not having abandoned
the fetters that he would realize
Nibbana that's not possible
so then consequently just goes the other
way who doesn't alike doesn't take
pleasure in company doesn't delight in
company he's an engaging company it is
possible for him to find pleasure in
seclusion when alone finding pleasure in
seclusion when alone that he will pick
up the side of the mind that is possible
it's not guaranteed he needs to make the
effort but it is possible because there
is a basis there is a further basis for
him picking up the sign of the mind
picking up side of the mind and he will
fulfill the right view that is also
possible having fulfilled that I view
that he will fulfill right Samadhi that
is also possible
having fulfilled the right Samadhi that
he would abandon the fetters that is
possible and having abandoned the
fetters that he really burner that is
possible
so that's why any and this applies to
lay people amongst well obviously the
marks but why goes to lay people and
anytime that you have to practice the
Dharma to reflect to read the suitors to
study you should try and do it alone
you should start cultivating seclusion
any chance to take a break from your
life in a sense of retreats or going
away from the usual busy environment you
should strive them you should strive for
the environment there would be solitary
because it takes effort like the these
things are described in this suit
they're not they're not automatic as I
said before so it's not like you just
need to extract yourself from the
company and you will then automatically
start finding pleasure in seclusion no
no no you cannot be in the company you
can be sort of separated from the group
but you would still be valuing that as a
pleasure you would still be valuing
company as pleasant you would still be
carrying mental delighting company even
if you're not engaging in physically so
you want to make the effort to approve
the pleasure that you find in company
and for that you need to be alone having
a brutal approach that you're finding
company then you can stop finding
pleasure in seclusion again it's not
automatic it's a clue so so it needs in
its in its work you need to put in the
work in order to start regarding
seclusion as pleasant feeling it
agreeably if you don't put in the work
it will not be agreeable and you know
whether it's agreeable or not if when
when you are secluded just see what what
do you mind us how are you reacting are
you looking for distraction are you are
you bearing are you feeling like you're
drowning or are you really really at
ease simply by being
simply by being
well that's what you should be striving
for so you realize even before you get
to the point of picking up the sign of
the mind as the suitor describes you
already have to put in a lot of work a
lot of enduring a lot of you draw a lot
of reflection and that's just in order
to find pleasure in seclusion and then
you can pick up the sign of the mind it
will it will basically outline itself
and then you get to discern it the
characteristics of the mind then you get
to know the mind at the time in whatever
state or mood it is for what it is so
that's another then layer of of work and
after effort you have to apply and then
goes to the right view which them is
described in the suitors obviously in
different ways but it's usually the four
Four Noble Truths understanding the
world softly understanding the nature of
suffering the escape from it and so on
but the point is none of these things
occur to you spontaneously none of these
things can occur just against the route
of your will or outside of your will
and certainly none of those things can
occur out of your meditation because as
as the next one says meditating rightly
without a right view is simply not
possible so your meditation your
seclusion your striving your effort your
study should all be pointing to one
thing there is no other alternative by
the way they should all be pointing to
getting the right view then you know
what to do and it's not like oh there's
just one approach to the Dhamma oh here
we teach the right view somewhere else
did know there is nothing else you can
teach there is no demo without the right
view so the right view is not the goal
Dhamma is not the goal as simple as that
and for those who wonder how fundamental
the right view is you can read much many
tiresome Aditi Sudha the right views of
them it's it determines the whole path
the right view it's not really optional
it's not really negotiable and and the
reason why we'll keep insisting that
it's important to kind of admit and keep
admitting this to yourself that without
the right view there is no Dhamma
because it's so easy to develop a false
sense of security and yeah I mean there
are teachings and meditation techniques
and so on that can make it peaceful and
help and help you but it's risky in a
sense that you can you can then easily
jump into the view that it's because
it's helpful it's the right thing to do
but the only way to know the right thing
to do is by having the right view so the
timing doesn't matter what experiences
you might be having on account of your
seclusion pleasant uplifting out of this
world the point is to know that it's
about knowing the right view not about
experiencing random things because if
you don't keep that context in your mind
if you don't keep your reminding
yourself of it you will then develop a
view that you know what's right what's
helpful what should be practiced while
at the same time you don't know you
don't have the right view and that's the
fundamental contradiction and but
because now you believe that you know
you won't be then making the effort to
to really find out why the right view is
because you allowed yourself a
concession that you can know what Dhamma
is you can't practice what Dhamma is you
can practice meditation according to the
Dhamma without having the right view and
that just that belief is easier is
basically a direct barricade to your
progress toward right view even if you
do everything else rightly having that
belief will be the obstacle to prevent
you from the right view because it's a
contradiction in terms
and if you don't abandon it you will not
be able to see it for yourself